North Country James Bay Group Records; Records apap327
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
North Country James Bay Group Records
1966-1998
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
North Country James Bay Group
apap327
1.2 cubic ft.
The North Country James Bay Group records document efforts of this upstate New York environmental organization to stop Hydro-Québec’s Great Whale (Grande Baleine) River/James Bay II development efforts in the early 1990s.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Margaret Weitzmann and Lucia Dailey donated materials in 2011 and 2012 to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Biographical Sketch
The James Bay hydroelectric project was an extensive build-up of hydroelectric power plants in the James Bay area and other nearby areas of Canada by Hydro-Québec. This multi-phase project began in 1972 with the construction of the first phase, the LaGrande complex. Nearly two decades later, plans for the multi-billion dollar James Bay II or Great Whale (Grande Baleine) River hydroelectric project called for the construction of dams, dikes, and reservoirs, the flooding of wilderness, removal of forest land, and the diversion of rivers. Similar action occurred with James Bay I. In light of environmental effects of the previous project and its negative impact upon the traditional lifestyle of the Cree people, the plans for James Bay II caused concern among native peoples of the area, scientists and environmental groups around the world. Plans were eventually stopped in the early 1990s after New York State withdrew from a billion dollar hydroelectric purchase agreement with Hydro-Québec in 1992 citing changed economic conditions, the Canadian government required Hydro-Québec to revise its environmental study prepared for James Bay II and the then Premier of Quebec, Jacques Parizeau, announced in 1994 that the project was being put on hold indefinitely.
The North Country James Bay Group was a New York-based grassroots organization dedicated to halting the development of the Great Whale River Project over concerns of a potential impact upon the environment, the rights of indigenous peoples living in the area and the argument that New York State did not need to purchase power from Hydro-Québec to meet its energy needs. North Country James Bay Group member Margaret Weitzmann, the principal donor of this collection, was a librarian and is now Faculty Emeriti for the State University of New York Potsdam campus. On behalf of the North Country James Bay Group, she spoke at public hearings, wrote articles and letters to the editor, attended and chaired conferences and participated in demonstrations against James Bay II.
Scope and Contents
The North Country James Bay Group Records document efforts of this upstate New York environmental organization to stop Hydro-Québec’s Great Whale (Grande Baleine) River/James Bay II development efforts in the early 1990s. This collection, donated by group members Margaret Weitzmann and Lucia Dailey, includes press releases, manuscripts and writings, fliers for rallies and events, conference materials, U.S. and Canadian newspaper clippings, statements made at public hearings, correspondence and subject files.
Separated Materials
Archivists transfered several multi-volume reports, including the Great Whale Environmental Assessment and Hydro-Québec’s Grande Baleine Complex Feasibility Study to Cataloging for inclusion in Minerva, the University Library catalog. After being cataloged, they will reside in the book division of Special Collections.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized alphabetically. There are no series.
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Native Americans; Conservation and the Environment; Conservation of natural resources--Canada; Cree Indians--James Bay Region--Social life and customs; Water-power--United States; Aquatic resources conservation--Canada; Wildlife conservation--Canada; James Bay (Nunavut); New York (State); James Bay Region--Environmental conditions.; Upstate New York (N.Y.); Speeches; Clippings; Correspondence; Official reports; Fliers (printed matter); Press Releases; North Country James Bay Group; Hydro-Québec; Power Authority of the State of New York; James Bay Hydroelectric Project
- Background Information on the Conformity and Quality Review of the Environmental Impact Statement for the Proposed Great Whale Project, Undated (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 1)
- Communications and Outreach, 1989-1994; 1997-1998; Undated (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 2)
- Conference, Albany 1994, 1993-1994; Undated (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 3)
- Conference, Cornell 1991 (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 4)
- Confernece, Montreal 1997, Undated (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 5)
- Correspondence from NYPA to Luke Dailey, 1991-1992 (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 6)
- Correspondence, M. Weitzmann, 1989-1994; 1997-1998; Undated (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 7)
- Current Issues: James Bay, Hydro-Québec and the Relationship with New York State, 1991 (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 8)
- Draft Guidelines for the Environmental Impact Study of the Great Whale Hydroelectric Project, 1992 (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 9)
- Environmental Impact Statement for the Proposed Great Whale Hydroelectric Project, 1992 (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 10-11)
- Fliers and Pamphlets, 1990-1992; 1997; Undated (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 12)
- Hydro-Québec Publications, 1989-1991; 1993 (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 13-14)
- Journal Articles, 1974; 1986; 1990-1992 (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 15)
- League of Women Voters, 1990-1992; Undated (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 16)
- Les Lignes a 735KV Baie James, 1977 (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 17)
- New York State Reports and Environmental Review, 1992 (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 18-19)
- Newspaper and Magazine Articles, 1979; 1982; 1985-1986; 1988-1994; Undated (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 20-21)
- Newspaper, Full Text, 1988; 1991-1992; Undated (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 22)
- Newspaper Items, Quebec/ James Bay, 1990-1994 (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 23-26)
- Press Releases, 1989-1994 (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 27)
- P.R.O.T.E.C.T, 1993-1994 (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 28)
- Public Hearings, Testimony, and Supplemental Materials, 1990-1995; Undated (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 29-30)
- Published Articles by Margaret Weitzmann, 1990-1991 (Box 1 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 31)
- Statement of Concerns and Recommendations for Protection and Enhancement Measures, 1975 (Box 2 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 1)
- Surface Water Data, Ungava Bay Drainage (1954-1963), 1966 (Box 2 (North Country James Bay Group Records ), Folder 2)